# 哈喽大家好我是王刚
Hey guys, this is Wang Gang
# 这两位是我的兄弟
These two are my buddies
# 哈喽大家好我们是华农兄弟
Hello everyone, we are Huanong Brothers
# 这是我四伯
This is my uncle
# 我是王刚的四伯
I am Wang Gang's uncle
# 国庆节就快要到了
National Day is coming
# 祖国的生日也快到了
so does the birthday of our country
# 过生日嘛 大家都很开心
birthday, y'know, everyone is happy for this
# 我想跟大家分享一道国宴菜
I wanna share with you a delicacy from the state banquet
# 当中比较有名的一个叫做清炖狮子头
a very famous one, called Qing Dun Shi Zi Tou (lit. braised lion head: braised pork meatballs)
# 然后今天我做红烧吧 好不好
Today I wanna cook it in red sauce
# 好
cool
# 做红烧来招待我这两位兄弟
to treat my two buddies
# 皮子给它去掉
remove the skin
# 然后先把肉切碎
and cut the meat into pieces
# 切碎了之后再剁一下
then mince it
# 其实做这个菜五花肉是最好的
In fact, pork belly suits this dish the best
# 半肥半瘦
half fat and half lean
# 把它剁一下
mince it
# 你过来嘛 兄弟
come on, bro
# 哇
wow
# 这个肉啊
this meat
# 猪肉哦
it's pork
# 来帮忙剁两刀好不好
could you help me a bit in mincing it
# 放点竹鼠肉下去
what about putting in some bamboo rat meat
# 啊
huh?
# 搞点竹鼠肉下去
get some meat of bamboo rats
# 我的天 你是什么时候都不会忘记的的竹鼠哦
omg, you never forget your bamboo rats
# 烧狮子头的肉稍微粗一点点就行了
the minced meat for Shi Zi Tou does not need to be mashed
# 来 你来剁一会儿
come on, I'll let you chop it for a while
# 我来
sure
# 哇
whoa
# 这刀太锋利了
the knife is so sharp
# 跟我们家的比起来
compared with that one in my home
# 我们家那个刀很钝哦
which is very blunt
# 你轻一点嘛
gentle
# 我觉得用你们家里养的那个土猪做出来肯定更好吃
I think it would taste better if we use the pig you raise
# 是
yup
# 每次来都不给我机会
you never give me the chance
# 下次来
next time
# 下次去我那里
next time you come to my house
# 现场烤一条给你
I will roast one for you on the spot
# 好 我来剁一会儿
Okay, let me chop it for a while
# 辛苦了辛苦了
thanks a lot
# 现在变成肉末了
It's becoming mince now
# 稍微剁一下就行了
just chop a few times
# 够不够啊 就那么一点点
seems not enough
# 这还要加其它配料
there are still other side ingredients to be added
# 加香菇 加莲藕 加胡萝卜
Shiitake, lotus roots, and carrots
# 哦
i see
# 可以了 这个剁成这样子就行了
Done. It is just fine to leave it like this
# 你们那边好像没有做这个菜吧
I never know people in your hometown cook this dish
# 没有
no
# 我们那边过年过节都是吃的那种肉圆
We eat a different kind of meatballs for festive celebration
# 你们切菜也是这样切吗
Do your people chop ingredients in this way?
# 我们切菜没有那么利索
I don't think we do it so agile and deft
# 这香菇也要切碎吗
Shiitake to be chopped as well?
# 也要切碎
Yes
# 切碎放进去
Put in the chopped shiitake
# 这个加香菇就不用放味精了
and you no longer need MSG
# 我在这里看着回去我都可以做了
Watching you here, I can definitely cook it by myself after I go back
# 切个葱都那么有技术
You are so skillful even at cutting scallions
# 你也可以啊
Sure you can do this as well
# 放一点盐
add a bit salt
# 这个就是调味调色
dark soy sauce for the colour
# 调色
...the colour
# 生抽调鲜味
light soy sauce for umami
# 好 差不多了
Okay, it's almost done
# 然后就是这样子抓
then is mixing all things together, in this way
# 我们一人抓一会儿好不好
we could do it in turn, couldn't we?
# 好
sure
# 这个还可以加一些剩的米饭进去
You can also add some cooked rice in it
# 米饭
rice!
# 对 也是为了增加口感
yup, it can also better the texture
# 也是很爽的
which will be excellent too
# 好 差不多了
cool, this step is finished
# 我们现在开始盘了啊
we now begin to roll the mince into meatballs
# 你看
y'see
# 好圆哦
it is so lovely round
# 对啊 圆圆的
yeah
# 现在闻不到香味
you can't sense the aroma right now
# 这个要炸了之后才有香味
it only gives out its aroma after being fried
# 好
okay
# 这个就盘好了
meatballs are shaped
# 然后我们就准备下锅制作
Let's start cooking
# 放宽油哦
Do you know what is this?
# 你知道这个是什么吗
Oh, Kuan You (lit. broad oil, a huge amount of oil)
# 宽油哦
you already know!
# 你都知道是宽油了
this is indeed Kuan You
# 这个确实是宽油
So much you pour in
# 放那么多
that's exactly why it is Kuan You
# 宽油了当然要宽了
It can't be Kuan You if it is not 'broad' enough
# 不宽怎么叫宽油呢
you fill half of the wok with oil for this dish
# 做这个菜油都放了半盆了
do you know how to check the temperature of the oil?
# 你会看油温吗
don't think so
# 不会
I learned that you need to stretch out your hand..
# 我最开始学的时候就是用手伸下去
really
# 真的
my hand's almost cooked
# 手都要熟
but now you can dip your finger in it
# 现在都可以伸下去
because the oil is not heated yet
# 现在油温好没烫呢
um
# 嗯
not boiling hot
# 还没烫
you can dip your hand in
# 都可以伸下去
You seldom get a chance to come here. I'm gonna teach you the way.
# 好不容易过来这个菜我教你
You stretch out your hand
# 试油温的时候手一伸
keep distance, do not touch the oil
# 不要挨着油离它远一点
feeling that it's a bit heated
# 感觉有点热了
you draw your hand back
# 好 你再伸出来
Wait a while and feel the temperature again
# 再烧一会儿又感觉一下
the temperature is just fine when the oil feels scalding
# 感觉有点烫手了油温就差不多了
You can put in the meatballs now
# 可以下肉了
which should slide in along the brim instead of being dropped
# 这个不能从中间放下去要从锅边溜下去
so delicate
# 那么讲究啊
of course
# 必须的
along the brim
# 要从锅边下去
ok
# 哦
yes
# 对
from the side
# 从锅边下去
you can softly push them a few times
# 可以轻轻的推一下
oh
# 哦
very tenderly
# 轻轻的推
I can smell the aroma now
# 现在都可以闻到香味了
true
# 对
fry them as such
# 就是这样炸它
after this you are gonna fry them one more time?
# 炸完之后等下又要煎
next you will use these
# 炸完之后就用这个
spices, ginger, and scallions, stir and fry them until the aroma comes out
# 香料姜葱下去炒出香味
then add some water
# 然后加水
later some light soy sauce, as well as sugar colour or dark soy sauce
# 然后加酱油糖色或者老抽
to enhance the colour
# 给它上色
and then do a bit seasoning
# 然后再调点味道
braise them in slow fire
# 慢慢的给它微（小火烧）
let the taste penetrate
# 把味道烧进去
for about half an hour and then thicken the sauce
# 烧大概半个小时然后就收汁
y'know, put in some starch
# 就勾点芡就可以
spread the sauce upon meatballs, sprinkle some chopped scallions, and it is ready to serve
# 把它淋在上面再撒点葱花就可以上菜了
wow, y'see, they become golden
# 哇 看到没有金黄辣
you can take them out now
# 差不多可以捞了
see
# 你看
how is it
# 怎么样
looks pretty good
# 可以起锅了
can be dredged up
# 但是这个捞出来了还要烧一会儿
need to be braised for a while though
# 现在已经炸香了
they have been fried to aromatic
# 真的很漂亮哦
They are very good-looking
# 好香啊
smell so good!
# 然后我们这个油
As for the oil
# 现在把它盛起来放着下次炸东西又可以用了
I take it out and save it for frying stuff next time
# 嗯
um
# 就不是说浪费
So it is not wasted
# 不存在浪费的
there is no problem of waste
# 然后我们锅里面要留一点油
we need to leave a bit oil in the wok
# 把这个香料放进去
put in the spices
# 还有这个姜葱
ginger and scallions
# 给它慢慢炒 炒出香味
slowly stir and fry to aromatic
# 这个爆香了然后我们就加水
add the water later on
# 好 大概加这么多
right, about this much
# 这个是老抽
this is dark soy sauce
# 然后放这个酱油
light soy sauce next
# 提鲜
to enhance the umami
# 再抖点盐下去
and a little bit salt
# 有点多哦
seems too much
# 放心吧这个没问题
it's fine, rest sure
# 然后这个我们加一点点白糖进去提一下鲜
Next, we put in a little sugar also for the umami
# 这个要盖上锅盖
seal the wok with the lid
# 现在我们把这个盖上
now we place the lid
# 盖上烧一会儿
braise a while
# 烧40分钟吧
about 40 minutes
# 那么久啊
that is a long time
# 那就烧半个小时吧
half an hour then
# 现在我把这个火烧得很旺哦
I have made a roaring fire
# 哇
wow
# 香吗
how does it smell
# 好香哦
the aroma is rich
# 可以了时间已经到了
okay, it's time
# 揭开锅盖
open the lid
# 现在捞起来
you see
# 你看
it is very tender inside
# 现在里面已经很软了
it has been braised so long that the sauce is half dried
# 炖了它那么久水都炖干一半了
yeah
# 然后我们加点这个水淀粉
Now we add some starch
# 把它勾成一个芡
to thicken the sauce
# 淀粉要一点点的放
the starch should be put in little by little
# 不能一次放太多
you should not put in too much at one time
# 为什么
why
# 因为你放太多掌握不好这个量的话
if you are unable to control the quantity
# 下去要嘛浓了 要嘛太稀了
the starch will be unfavourably thick or thin
# 哦
i see
# 再放一点点
a bit more
# 好
good
# 淋在这个上面
spread the sauce upon them
# 然后在中间撒一点葱花
and scatter the chopped scallions
# 爸爸
papa!
# 诶
eh?
# 我也要吃那个
I wanna eat that too
# 好 你要吃“狮子头”啊
ok, you wanna have Shi Zi Tou?
# 要
yup
# 粗鲁一点啊
let's be a bit reckless
# 快拦住它不要它跑出来
keep it inside, don't let it escape!
# 可以了
it's finished
# 兄弟 火稍微停一下
bro, could you put out the fire for a while
# 兄弟你尝一个
have a taste
# 没关系 你尝一个蟹看熟了没有
see if it is well done
# 熟了 里面都熟了
it's been cooked thoroughly
# 熟了吧 好
good good
# 熟了那我就熟虾了哦
I'm going to cook the shrimps then
# 嗯
um
# 把虾煮下去就差不多了
we can start the meal once the shrimps are cooked
# 姜也放下去
add some ginger
# 这个葱也放下去
also these scallions
# 哇
whoa
# 准备吃饭啦
it's time for dinner!
# 好开饭了
Dinner time!
# 其实这个菜（红烧狮子头）是淮扬菜
This Hong Shao Shi Zi Tou (lit. red-cooked lion head, red-cooked pork meatballs) is a kind of Huai Yang dishes
# 嗯
um
# 对 以前我们周总理很喜欢吃这道菜
In the past, our prime minister Zhou was very fond of it
# 那道菜是国宴菜
this dish therefore became a state banquet cuisine
# 然后做得很清淡
it is cooked with a mild taste
# 但是我们这个的话为了更下饭一点
But I try to make it go better with rice
# 所以就做成红烧
so I do it in the red-cooked way
# 我自己剥龙虾
I will peel the shrimp by myself
# 不错哦，自己都可以剥
good job - do it all on your own
# 像以前一样
like in the past
# 我们还小的时候
when I was a child
# 生活很困难
the time was hard
# 对
true
# 逢年过节才有肉吃
I had meat only during festivals and on other important dates
# 不像现在几乎每顿都可以吃肉
unlike the things now, we can have meat in every meal
# 我们小时候也是一样的
I experienced the same when I was a child
# 就是可能
it is probably
# 十天半个月才能看见一点点肉
every ten days to half a month that I saw a little meat in my meal
# 所以在这里我们祝我们伟大的祖国
Therefore, I wanna wish our great home country
# 生日快乐
Happy Birthday!
# 好了 拜拜
Okay, bye~